it's the real news I'm Aaron Matty
Chelsea Manning is celebrated around the
world for exposing the secrets of u.s.
foreign policy including war crimes and
going to prison for it
all the while standing up for her rights
as a trans woman but one of the most
prestigious US schools has taken a
different view the Harvard Kennedy
School has rescinded an invitation to
Manning as a visiting fellow after a
backlash led by current and former
officials former CIA deputy director
Michael Morell resigned as a Harvard
fellow in protest writing quote I have
an obligation to my conscience
the current CIA director Mike Pompeo
withdrew from a Harvard forum where he
was set to speak Pompeyo said quote it
has everything to do with her identity
as a traitor to the US and Lyle Oil T to
the officers of the CIA this prompted
Harvard Kennedy School Dean Douglas
Elmendorf to announce he would still
invite Manning to speak on campus but is
withdrawing her designation as a
visiting fellow Elmendorf wrote quote I
see more clearly now that many people
view a visiting fellow title as an
honorific so we should weigh that
consideration when offering invitations
joining me is someone who knows about
the consequences of government
whistleblowing John Kiriakou is a former
CIA analyst who exposed the agency's
torture program and became the only
fishel jailed in connection with it John
welcome thanks for having me happy to be
with you again thank you for joining us
your reaction to Harvard's decision to
tell you the truth I was disgusted by
Harvard and by its decision for a couple
of reasons it was it was bad enough that
the John F Kennedy School of Government
disinvited Chelsea Manning but then to
to try to justify its actions it dug
itself deeper in a hole CIA director
Mike Pompeo made a ridiculous
hypocritical statement today saying that
or yesterday I should say saying that
Harvard had traded someone who had sir
this country with respect and dignity
for someone who had committed treason
against her country that is preposterous
and let me tell you why I worked for 14
and a half year was years with Mike
Morell I know Mike Morell well Mike
Morell was instrumental in implementing
the CIA's torture program Mike Morell
was instrumental in implementing the
CIA's program of secret prisons around
the world Mike Morell was instrumental
in implementing the CIA's extraordinary
rendition program which is just an extra
legal kidnapping program that is not
serving your country with respect and
with dignity that is committing
international crimes against humanity so
I would trade Mike Morell for Chelsea
Manning any day of the week Harvard made
a grave mistake you know John the irony
there in looking at morels record if you
look at the letter that he wrote as I
read explaining why he was resigning in
protest of the invitation to Manning he
said quote I have an obligation to my
conscience I'm sorry III don't mean to
laugh out loud but but it's laughable
where was his conscience when we were
murdering people in enterin during
interrogations at the CIA where was his
conscience where we were creating these
dungeons in former country in foreign
countries to to torture people in he had
no conscience
and now his conscience tells him that he
can't serve not even not even in the
same in the same program but in the same
school with with a whistleblower a woman
who meets the very definition of
whistleblowing which is bringing to
light any evidence of waste fraud abuse
or illegality that's exactly what
Chelsea Manning did let me also reach
you more from Mike Pompeo the director
of the CIA who you mentioned he wrote in
defending Morell's decision he wrote it
has everything to do with her identity
as a traitor to the United States of
America and my loyalty to the officers
of the CIA
accusing Manning of treason that's a
charge that she was not convicted of no
I mean Mike Pompeo isn't as smart as he
would like to think that he is there's
of course a legal definition of treason
and Chelsea Manning and Chelsea
Manning's actions bear no resemblance
whatsoever to the to the constitutional
definition of treason Mike Pompeo is a
politician and he's a politician who's
in over his head
he's out of his element he simply
doesn't know what he's talking about
you know John if you could help me do a
little bit of psychoanalysis here what
do you think goes on in the minds of
people like Mike Morell Mike Pompeo all
those who are so outraged so livid over
granting someone like Chelsea Manning
who stood up for her conscience and went
to jail for it
granting her a you know relatively mild
honor a visiting fellowship it's not
like she got the Nobel Peace Prize which
of course many people think she should
get but what do you think goes on in
their minds when they see this happen
and why they react so angrily in
response I think that that the likes of
Morrell and Pompeyo and Tennant and Phil
Mudd and Steve kappes and all these
other people Jose Rodriguez all these
other people who have been implicated in
the CIA's torture program and other
extrajudicial programs have to double
down they have they have made decisions
over the courses of their CIA careers
that are indefensible but when they die
and their obituaries are written the
first thing that's going to be mentioned
is these programs and so they have to
repeat this lie over and over and over
again that things like the torture
program and the rendition program and
the secret prisons were illegal and
somehow benefited the American people
and kept the country safe they have to
keep repeating that lie hoping that if
they say it enough times the American
people will finally come to believe it
so when someone like Chelsea Manning
gets as you say this this very you know
not that big of a deal honor to be a
visiting fellow at Harvard the torturers
have to double down right and finally
John you know you're talking about how
these people will be remembered and
remembered for the crimes that they
oversaw well the reason that they'll be
remembered for that if that happens is
because people exposed it people like
Manning and people like yourself and I'm
wondering seeing how Manning is treated
you know now and of course with a prison
sentence you also went to prison I'm
wondering if you talked about the just
the the difficulty of being a
whistleblower where you are you face
such punishment not only you know after
you're caught for the Act but then
society people in power still continue
to treat you with scorn and disdain oh
yeah unless your name is you know
Scooter Libby for example or David
Petraeus unless you're a friend of the
President or you have four shiny stars
on your shoulder you're pretty well
ruined you know the goal is not just to
give you a year or two or seven in
prison the goal is to ruin you
permanently not just because they don't
like you but because they want to make
an example of you so that other people
don't take your cue and blow the whistle
on waste fraud abuse and illegality you
know it's it's whistleblowers that that
bring down these illegal programs and
the powers that be in places like the
CIA or the White House or the Pentagon
won't stand for it John Kerry aku is the
former CIA analysts who went to prison
for exposing the torture program now
he's the co-host of the show
loud and clear with Brian Becker on
radio Sputnik John thanks very much my
pleasure thanks for having me and thank
you for joining us on the real news